Herbert Hitchen Irish Collection, 1908-1970
Mortimer Rare Book Room, William Allan Neilson Library, Smith College
Herbert Hitchen Irish Collection
1908-1970
Hitchen, Herbert, 1874-1979
10
3 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Mortimer Rare Book Room Smith College Northampton, MA
Pastor of the Unitarian Church of Northampton, Massachusetts, 1958-1966, and an avid collector of Irish literature. Hitchen, born in Norland, Yorkshire, formed his collection around publications from the Cuala Press, a small press in Dublin owned by Elizabeth C. Yeats, as well as manuscript material from poets and playwrights such as Joseph Campbell, Lennox Robinson, Jack B. Yeats, Willam B. Yeats, and George Russell. Consists of broadsides, correspondence, photographs, catalogs, clippings, prospectuses, and publications concerned with modern Irish literature, mainly from the period known as the Irish Renaissance.
The Herbert Hitchen Irish collection consists of broadsides, correspondence, photographs, catalogs, clippings, prospectuses, and publications concerned with modern Irish literature, mainly from the period known as the Irish Renaissance. Herbert Hitchen (1874-1979) was born in Norland, Yorkshire. He was pastor of the Unitarian Church of Northampton, Massachusetts, 1958-1966, and was an avid collector of Irish literature. Hitchen formed his collection around publications from the Cuala Press, a small press in Dublin owned by Elizabeth C. Yeats, as well as manuscript material from poets and playwrights such as Joseph Campbell, Lennox Robinson, Jack B. Yeats, Willam B. Yeats, and George Russell (also known as AE). The collection was purchased by Smith College from Herbert Hitchen in 1965, and rare materials were transferred to the Mortimer Rare Book Room. The Herbert Hitchen Irish Collection consists of 134 folders arranged in 2 boxes and one oversize box. Box 1 contains folders 1-60. Box 2 contains folders 61-128. The Oversize box contains folders A-F. All material is arranged alphabetically within each series by main entry, and then chronologically.
This collection is organized into seven series:
I. Broadsides, 1921-1937
II. Catalogs, 1965-1970
III. Clippings
IV. Correspondence
V. Photographs and Etchings
VI. Prospectuses
VII. Publications
The Herbert Hitchen Irish Collection consists of 134 folders arranged in 2 boxes and one oversize box. Box 1 contains folders 1-60. Box 2 contains folders 61-128. The Oversize box contains folders A-F. All material is arranged alphabetically within each series by main entry, and then chronologically.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The Herbert Hitchen Irish Collection is the physical property of the Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College. Literary rights, including copyright, belong to the authors of works or their legal representatives.
History of the Collection
The collection was purchased by Smith College from Herbert Hitchen in 1965, and rare materials were transferred to the Mortimer Rare Book Room.
Search Terms
Hitchen, Herbert.; Cuala Press.; English literature--Irish authors--20th century.; English literature--20th century.; Irish literature--20th century.; Campbell, Joseph, 1879-1944.; Robinson, Lennox, 1886-1958.; Russell, George William, 1867-1935.; Yeats, Jack Butler, 1871-1957.; Yeats, W. B. (William Butler), 1865-1939.; Yeats, Elizabeth Corbet, 1868-1940.; Cuala Press.
- Series I. Broadsides--Cuala Press, 1921-1937, (24 items), (folders 1-21)
  Series I consists of broadsides, hand colored and produced by the Cuala Press.
- Series II. Catalogs, 1965-1970, (8 items), (folders 22-29)
  Series II consists of catalogs.
- Series III. Clippings, 1927-1939, (folders 30-38)
  Series III consists of press clippings.
- Series IV. Correspondence, 1927-1950, (folders 39-106)
  Series IV consists of correspondence to Hitchen, primarily from his long-standing friendships with Lennox Robinson and Joseph Campbell.
- Series V. Photographs and Etchings, 1914-1941, (folders 107-113)
  Series V consists of photographs and etchings, featuring George Russell and Seumus O'Sullivan.
- Series VI. Prospectuses, (folders 114-115)
  Series VI consists of prospectuses.
- Series VII. Publications, (folders 116-128)
  Series VII consists of publications.
- Series VIII. Oversize, 1927-1930
- Series I. Broadsides--Cuala Press, 1921-1937
  - Carberry, Ethna. "There is a way I am fain to go," [undated]. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cluna Studio. "Achill," undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cluna Studio. Letts, W. M. "A blessing," undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cluna Studio. "The little road says go," undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cluna Studio. O'Mahony, N. Tynan. "For I'm lonesome in the city," undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Colum, Padraic. "The Captive Archer," Aug 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Colum, Padraic. "Carrick nabauna," Nov 1911 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gogarty, Oliver St. John, "Non Dolet," Feb 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Higgins, F.R., "Glory O!," Jul 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - K. "Thy waters are silent, thy shores are wide," undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lawless, Emily. "I see an envied haunt of peace," undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - O'Sullivan, Seumus. "Ambition in Cuffe Street," Oct 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Autographed by O'Sullivan, Jack B. Yeats.
  - O'Sullivan, Seumus. "Funerals," 2 copies. Mar 1910 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - O'Sullivan, Seumus. "Nelson Street," 3 copies. Jun 1910 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    2 copies autographed by O'Sullivan, Jack B. Yeats.
  - O'Sullivan, Seumus. "Tim the fiddler," undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Rio Grande Capstan Chanty," Inside: Stephens, James, "Where the demons grin. Nov 1908 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Autographed by Stephens, Jack B. Yeats.
  - Stephens, James. "The Main Deep," Apr 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Stephens, James. "The Rivals," Jun 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Yeats, W.B. "Come gather round me Parnellites," Jan 1937 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Yeats, W.B. "The Curse of Cromwell," Aug 1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Yeats, W.B. "The Three bushes," Mar 1937 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Broadsides. Cuala Press. undated
    See: Oversize:A
- Series II. Catalogs, 1965-1970
  - Richard Abel & Co. 25 May 1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bibliographia Hibernica Autumn 1965-Spring 1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Blackwell's Catalogue 814 undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Blackwell's Catalogue 825 undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Brick Row Book Shop 1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Emerald Isle Books Spring 1966 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - House of Books, Ltd. undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Olin Library, Wesleyan University. "William Butler Yeats." 1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Series III. Clippings, 1927-1939
  - "Amateurs trained in Irish Classics," New York Evening Journal. [reproduction]. 17 Jun 1926 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "The Book Table: the later Mr. Yeats," by Herbert S. Gorman. The Outlook. undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Campbell, Joseph. "Towns." 1 Oct 1920 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Ireland's culture subject of lecture." undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Irish repertory players present 'Candida'," The Billboard. 29 Jan 1938 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Maunsel & Co. Miscellaneous advertisements and catalog entries. undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Newspaper Photograph: James Joyce, James Stephens, John O'Sullivan. undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Review of The Interpreters, by A.E. The Nation. 25 Apr 1923 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - [Obituary] "W.B. Yeats, 73, Irish Poet and Playwright." 1939 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Says Pied Piper Legend is true," New York Sun. Article featuring interview with William Starkey. 29 Mar 1930
    See: Oversize B
  - "St. Patrick and the Shamrock," World Magazine. Joseph Campbell tells legend in interview. 13 Mar 1927
    See: Oversize C
- Series IV. Correspondence, 1927-1950
  - Campbell, Joseph
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 23 Mar 1927 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Autograph cards signed: Announcements for School of Irish Studies. 30 Mar 1927-13 Jan 1939 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 1 Sep 1928 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Autograph letter, signed. 15 Sep 1928 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Autograph letter, signed. 18 Sep 1928 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      [With: copy of typed letter, signed, Lawrence Clare to Herbert Hitchen, 24 Sep 1928. See folder 56 for original.]
    - Autograph letter, signed. 21 Sep 1928 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Autograph letter, signed. 8 Feb 1930 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 23 Mar 1930 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 4 Jan 1931 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 5 Nov 1931 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Telegram. 27 Nov 1931 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Autograph card, signed, with envelope. 22 Dec 1931 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Autograph card, signed, with envelope. 29 Mar 1932 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Autograph card, signed, with envelope. 26 Dec 1934 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Autograph card, signed, with envelope. 12 May 1938 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Telegram. 2 Apr [undated] (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Plain brown wrapping paper, addressed to Hitchen in Campbell's hand. undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Clare, Laurence
    - Typed letter, signed. 24 Sep 1928 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      [With: copy of autographed letter, signed, from Joseph Campbell to Lawrence Clare. See folder 43 for original.]
  - Cousins, James H.
    - Typed letter, signed, with envelope. 2 Apr 1932 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Dunham, Franklin
    - Telegram to Walter Starkie, care of Herbert Hitchen. 10 Apr 1930 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Hitchen, Herbert
    - Cancelled check, to Joseph Campbell. 14 Mar 1927 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Envelopes, addressed to Hitchen. undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Robinson, Lennox
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 14 Nov 1928 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Autograph card, signed. 22 Dec 1928 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 19 Jan 1929 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Autograph card, signed. 27 Jul 1930 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Autograph card, signed. 13 Dec 1930 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Typed letter, signed, with envelope. 28 Sep 1931 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Telegram. 29 Sep 1931 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 10 Nov 1931 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 17 Nov 1931 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Autograph card, signed. 1931 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Typed letter, signed, with envelope. 3 May 1932 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Autograph card, signed. 1932 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 6 Jan 1934 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Autograph card, signed. 17 Jun 1934 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Autograph card, signed. 1935 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Typed letter, signed, with envelope. [With: pamphlet, "Memorial to George W. Russell (AE)."] 31 Jan 1936 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Typed letter, signed, with envelope. 27 May 1936 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Autograph card, signed, with envelope. 11 Dec 1937 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Typed letter, signed, with envelope. 16 Jun 1938 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Typed letter, signed. 21 Jul 1938 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 9 Dec 1938 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Autograph card, signed, with envelope. 2 Dec 1939 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Typed card. 31 Dec 1940 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 13 Dec 1947 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Typed letter, signed. 15 Dec [1947] (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 26 Dec 1947 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 5 Feb 1948 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Autograph card, signed. 23 Jun 1948 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Autograph card, signed. 16 Jul 1948 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 22 Jan 1948 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Autograph card, signed. 1 Sep 1948 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Autograph card, signed. Dec 1948 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Autograph card, signed, with envelope. 12 Dec 1950 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - 4 envelopes, addressed to Hitchen. 1929-1947 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Telegraph. 22 Dec [undated] (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Autograph card, signed. undated (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Autograph card, signed, with envelope. undated (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Plain brown wrapping paper. undated
      See: Oversize:D
  - Starkie, Walter
    - Autograph letter, signed, with envelope. 13 Apr 1930 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Notes to Yellow Cab Co., Chicago. undated (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Text for Telegram. undated (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Vinal, Harold
    - Typed letter, signed, addressed to Vinal 18 Dec 1931 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Yeats, Elizabeth C.
    - Autograph letter, signed. 8 Oct 1929 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Autograph letter, signed. 30 Nov 1929 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Autograph letter, signed. 5 Jan 1930 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Autograph letter, signed. 26 Jul 1932 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Holograph note, not signed, on Cuala Industries letterhead. undated (Box 2, Folder 106)
- Series V. Photographs and Etchings, 1914-1941
  - "It is given to few to create - to enjoy should be the inalienable birthright of all!" Cameo portrait on tissue, with mat. undated
    See: Oversize E
  - Campbell, Joseph
    - Photograph of portrait by Estelle Soloman. Autographed by Campbell, with envelope. undated (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Fisher, A. Hugh
    - Original sketch of James Stephens, autographed by Stephens. 1941 (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Signed Etching of George Russell (AE). undated (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Robinson, Lennox
    - 2 autographed portraits of Robinson. Nov 1931 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - Russell, George (AE)
    - Reproduction of a line drawing portrait, autographed by Russell. Artist's signature: W.R., Dublin. Nov 1914 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Two photographs of Russell's grave, and one portrait of Russell. undated (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - Photograph of George Russell (AE) and Seumus O'Sullivan, in O'Sullivan's garden, sent to Hitchen by Russell. undated (Box 2, Folder 113)
- Series VI. Prospectuses
  - Cuala Press. Miscellaneous prospectuses. undated (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Cuala Press. Miscellaneous prospectuses. undated
    See: Oversize F
  - Renvyle House Hotel. undated (Box 2, Folder 115)
- Series VII. Publications
  - Abbey Theatre, Dublin. Theatre festival flyer with autographed note by Lennox Robinson. Aug 1938 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Advertisement for lecture by Lennox Robinson in aid of Dunkirk Free Library. 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - Advertisement for lecture by Walter Starkie. Feb-Apr 1929 (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Announcement of the School of Irish Studies. Autographed by Campbell [pages 11 and 33]. 1928 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Announcement of the School of Irish Studies. Autographed by Campbell [page 10]. 1929 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - The Arrow. W. B. Yeats Commemorative number. Summer 1939 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Circum-Spice. June 1970 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Cuala Press. Four Christmas cards. One signed by Jack B. Yeats, autograph greetings from Fred W. Robinson. undated (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - Cuala Press. Photocopies of prospectuses and catalogs. undated (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - Feis Oidhche Bhealtaine. 1 May 1938, [program] (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - The Fiery Arrow. Dec 1929, [2 copies] (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - Press releases and invitation for opening of Robinson's "The Lucky Finger." Jan 1948 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - School of Irish Studies. Syllabus. 1926 (Box 2, Folder 128)
- Series VIII. Oversize, 1927-1930
  - BROADSIDES
    - Miscellaneous Broadsides. Cualla Press. undated (Box 3, Folder A)
  - CLIPPINGS
    - "Says Pied Piper Legend is true," New York Sun. Article featuring interview with William Starkey. 29 Mar 1930 (Box 3, Folder B)
    - "St. Patrick and the Shamrock," World Magazine. Joseph Campbell tells all in interview. 13 Mar 1927 (Box 3, Folder C)
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Plain brown wrapping paper. undated (Box 3, Folder D)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS AND ETCHINGS
    - "It is given to few to create-to enjoy should be the inalienable birthright of all!" Cameo portrait on tissue, with mat. undated (Box 3, Folder E)
  - PROSPECTUSES
    - Cuala Press. Miscellaneous prospectuses. undated (Box 3, Folder F)